Thank you. I have two missions here today.
شكرأً .. لدي مهمتين اليوم ..
The first is to tell you something about pollen, I hope,
الأولى هي أن أخبركم شيئاً عن حبوب اللقاح - وأتمنى -
and to convince you that it's more than just something that gets up your nose.
أن أقنعكم أنها شيء أكثر من مجرد شيء يمكنه أن يدخل في أنفك
And, secondly, to convince you
والثاني هو أن أقنعكم
that every home really ought to have a scanning electron microscope.
بأن كل منزل يتوجب عليه أن يملك مجهرا الكترونيا للمسح
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Pollen is a flower's way of making more flowers.
إن حبوب اللقاح هي وسيلة الأزهار لإنتاج أزهار أُخرى
It carries male sex cells
حيث أنها تحمل الخلايا الذكرية الجنسية
from one flower to another.
من زهرة إلى أُخرى
This gives us genetic diversity,
وهذا هو الذي يعطينا التنوع الجيني
or at least it gives the plants genetic diversity.
أو على الأقل يعطي النباتات التنوع الجيني الذي تملكه
And it's really rather better not to mate with yourself.
بدلاً من أن تتكاثر مع نفسها
That's probably true of humans as well, mostly.
وهو الأمر الذي ينطبق على معظم البشر عادة .
Pollen is produced by the anthers of flowers.
تنتج حبوب اللقاح في " الميسم "
Each anther can carry up to 100,000 grains of pollen,
وكل ميسم يحمل 100000 من حبوب اللقاح
so, it's quite prolific stuff.
لذا فهي منتشرة بغزارة
And it isn't just bright flowers
وليست فقط الأزهار الملونة هي التي تملك حبوب اللقاح
that have pollen; it's also trees and grasses.
فحتى الأشجار والأعشاب
And remember that all our cereal crops are grasses as well.
وتذكروا إن كل الحبوب التي نأكلها هي في الأصل أعشاب
Here is a scanning electron micrograph of a grain of pollen.
وهنا ترون مسح إلكتروني ميكروغرافي لحبة لقاح
The little hole in the middle, we'll come to a bit later,
وسوف نعود للفتحة الصغير الموجودة في المنتصف لاحقا للتحدث عنها ..
but that's for the pollen tube
والتي هي مخصصة لأُنبوب اللقاح
to come out later on. A very tiny tube.
الذي يخرج لاحقا .. وهو أنبوب صغيرٌ جداً
So, that's 20 micrometers across,
وهذه عرضها 20 ميكروميتر
that pollen grain there.
أقصد حبة اللقاح تلك
That's about a 50th of a millimeter.
وهذه تقريباً 50 ميليميتر
But not all pollen is quite so simple looking.
ولكن ليس جميع حبات اللقاح لها شكل متشابه
This is Morina. This is a plant --
هذه " مورينيا " وهذه نبته
which I've always thought to be rather tedious --
أتصور أنها يجب أن تسمى بدلاً من إسمها الممل هذا
named after Morin,
بإسم " مورا "
who was an enterprising French gardener,
والتي كانت مزارعة فرنسية منتجة ..
who issued the first seed catalog
حيث أصدرت أول دليل للبذور في
in 1621.
عام 1621
But anyway, take a look at its pollen.
على كلٍ .. أُنظروا إلى حبة اللقاح هذه
This is amazing, I think.
إنها مدهشة كما أعتقد
That little hole in the middle there is for the pollen tube,
إن الفتحة الصغيرة في المنتصف هنا .. والتي هي لأنبوب اللقاح
and when the pollen finds its special female spot
حيث عندما تجد حبة اللقاح منطقتها الأُنثوية المميزة
in another Morina flower,
في زهرة " مورينا "
just on the right species, what happens?
اي في الفصيلة نفسها .. مالذي يحدث ؟
Like I said, pollen carries the male sex cells.
كما قلت سابقاً .. إن حبوب اللقاح تحمل الخلايا الذكرية
If you actually didn't realize that plants have sex,
وإن لم تنتبهوا لهذا من قبل .. فالنباتات تمارس الجنس ..
they have rampant, promiscuous
ويمارسون عملية جنسية مختلطة .. وكثيفة
and really quite interesting and curious sex. Really.
وهي مثيرة للإهتمام والفضول في الواقع أيضاً
(Laughter) A lot.
(ضحك)
My story is actually not about plant propagation,
في الحقيقة لا اريد التحدث عن تكاثر النباتات
but about pollen itself.
بل عن حبة اللقاح نفسها
"So, what are pollen's properties?" I hear you ask.
وأعتقد أنكم تسألون الآن ماهي مميزات حبة اللقاح
First of all, pollen is tiny. Yes we know that.
أولا .. حبة اللقاح صغيرة جداً . وأنتم تعلمون هذا
It's also very biologically active,
وهي نشطة بيولوجيا جداً
as anyone with hay fever will understand.
وأي شخص يملك حساسية الربيع يمكنه أن يعي هذا جيداً
Now, pollen from plants, which are wind-dispersed --
إن حبوب اللقاح والتي تنتشر عبر الرياح
like trees and grasses and so on --
من النباتات والأشجار والأعشاب .. وهلمجراً
tend to cause the most hay fever.
هي أهم مسببات معظم حمى " القش " التي تصيبنا
And the reason for that is they've got to chuck out
وسبب هذا أن النباتات عليها أن تنشر
masses and masses of pollen to have any chance
الكثير والكثير من حبوب اللقاح في الأجواء لكي يغطي كل السبل
of the pollen reaching another plant of the same species.
للوصول إلى النبتة الأُخرى من الفصيلة نفسها
Here are some examples --
وهذه بعض الأمثلة
they're very smooth if you look at them --
إن نظرتم إليها فهي تبدو ملساء جدا..
of tree pollen that is meant to be carried by the wind.
وهذه حبوب اللقاح الخاصة بالأشجار وهي مخصصة لكي تنقل بواسطة الرياح
Again -- this time, sycamore -- wind-dispersed.
وهذه لشجرة الجميز ,, وهي أيضاً تنتشر بواسطة الرياح
So, trees: very boring flowers,
في الحقيقة الأشجار أزهار مملة جداً
not really trying to attract insects.
فهي لا تستهدف جذب الحشرات ..
Cool pollen, though.
هذه حبة لقاح رائعة
This one I particularly like.
وأنا أفضل هذه بالتحديد
This is the Monterey Pine, which has little air sacks
وهي خاصة بصنوبر " مونتيري " ولديها مخدات هوائية
to make the pollen carry even further.
لكي يسهل حملها مسافة أبعد
Remember, that thing is just about 30 micrometers across.
تذكروا بعد هذه الحبة تقريباً 30 ميركوميتر
Now, it's much more efficient if you can get insects to do your bidding.
الآن ولفعالية أكثير يتم إستخدام الحشرات لعملية التلقيح
This is a bee's leg
هذه هنا رجل نحلة
with the pollen glommed onto it from a mallow plant.
معلق عليها حبات لقاح من نبات الملوخية
And this is the outrageous and beautiful
وهذه زهرة مغامرة وجميلة
flower of the mangrove palm.
من نخيل " مانجروف "
Very showy, to attract lots of insects to do its bidding.
وهي واضحة جداً ومخصصة لجذب العديد من الحشرات للتخصيب
The pollen has little barbs on it,
وحبة اللقاح هذه تملك شعيرات على سطحها
if we look.
إذا نظرتم هنا
Now, those little barbs
وهذه الشعيرات الصغيرة
obviously stick to the insects well,
هدفها كما هو واضح الإلتصاق بالحشرات
but there is something else that we can tell from this photograph,
ولكن هنالك شيء آخر يمكن تبينه من هذه الصورة
and that is that you might be able to see a fracture line
وهو أنه يمكنكم رؤية خط إنكسار
across what would be the equator of this, if it was the Earth.
يمر عبر حبة اللقاح كما لو أنه خط الأستواء في الأرض
That tells me that it's actually been fossilized, this pollen.
وهذا يخبرنا أن حبة اللقاح تلك متحضرة .. وحبة اللقاح
And I'm rather proud to say
هذه وأفتخر أن أقول
that this was found just near London, and that 55 million years ago
وجدت في مكان بالقرب من لندن .. ومنه فإنه منذ 55 مليون سنة
London was full of mangroves.
كانت لندن مليئة بنخل " المنجاروف "
Isn't that cool?
أليس هذا رائعا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Okay, so this is another species evolved to be dispersed by insects.
حسناً .. هذا صنف آخر تطور لكي يتم نقله أيضاً بواسطة الحشرات
You can tell that from the little barbs on there.
ويمكنكم تبين هذا من الشعيرات الصغيرة الموجودة هنا
All these pictures were taken with a scanning electron microscope,
وبالمناسبة جيمع هذه الصور تم إلتقاطها بواسطة ميكروسكوب إلكتروني
actually in the lab at Kew Laboratories.
في مخبر تابع لمخابر " كيو "
No coincidence that these were taken
ولا عجب أن هذه الصور أُلتقطت بواسطة
by Rob Kesseler, who is an artist,
" روب كيسلير " والذي هو في الأساس فنان
and I think it's someone with a design and artistic eye
والذي أعتقد أنه شخص يملك حس التصميم ونظرة الفنان
like him that has managed to bring out the best in pollen.
التي مكنته من إظهار أفضل ما يمكن من صور حبات اللقاح
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, all this diversity
الآن كل هذا التنوع
means that you can look at a pollen grain
يعني أنه من الممكن النظر إلى حبة اللقاح
and tell what species it came from,
وتبين أي فصيلة تنتمي إليها
and that's actually quite handy if you
وهذا مفيد جداً
maybe have a sample and you want to see where it came from.
إذا كنت تملك عينة من " شيء " وتريد تبين مكانه الأصلي
So, different species of plants
لان النباتات المختلفة تنمو
grow in different places,
في أماكن مختلفة
and some pollen carries further than others.
وبعض حبات اللقاح تحمل لمناطق أبعد من غيرها
So, if you have a pollen sample,
وإذا كنت تملك حبة لقاح
then in principle, you should be able to tell
فإنه نظريا يمكنك تبين
where that sample came from.
المكان الذي جاءت منه
And this is where it gets interesting for forensics.
وهذا الأمر مثير للإهتامام بالنسبة للطب الشرعي
Pollen is tiny. It gets on to things, and it sticks to them.
لان حبوب اللقاح صغيرة جدا .. وهي منتشرة .. وتلتصق بالأشياء
So, not only does each type of pollen look different,
وليس فقط كل نوع من حبوب اللقاح مختلف عن الآخر
but each habitat has a different combination of plants.
بل إن أي منطقة لديها مجموعة من النباتات خاصة بها
A different pollen signature, if you like,
أي توقيع " بحبوب اللقاح " خاص بها
or a different pollen fingerprint.
أو بصمة " حبوب اللقاح " الخاصة بها
By looking at the proportions and combinations
وبالنظر إلى النسب والخليط
of different kinds of pollen in a sample,
من حبوب اللقاح تلك في العينة
you can tell very precisely where it came from.
يمكننا وبكل دقة تبين المكان الذي جاءت منه تلك العينة
This is some pollen embedded in a cotton shirt,
هذه بعض حبوب اللقاح متعلقة في قميص قطني
similar to the one that I'm wearing now.
مشابه للذي أرتديه الآن
Now, much of the pollen will still be there
والعديد من حبوب اللقاح ستبقي في ذلك القميص
after repeated washings.
حتى بعد غسله مراراً
Where has it been?
أي كان هذا القميص ؟
Four very different habitats might look similar,
هذه أربع مناطق تبدو متشابهة
but they've got very different pollen signatures.
لكن كل منها يملك توقيعا خاص به بواسطة حبوب اللقاح
Actually this one is particularly easy, these pictures were all taken
في الحقيقة يبدو هذا سهل للغاية .. فهذه الصور إلتقطت
in different countries.
في دول مختلفة
But pollen forensics can be very subtle.
ولكن الطبيب الشرعي الذي ينظر إلى حبوب اللقاح يمكنه أن يكون متأكداً من المكان
It's being used now to track
وهذه الطريقة تستخدم الآن
where counterfeit drugs have been made,
لتعقب مواقع إنتاج العقاقير المزيفة
where banknotes have come from,
ومواقع تزوير الأموال
to look at the provenance of antiques
وحتى المناطق التي جاءت منها التحف الأثرية
and see that they really did come from the place
والتأكد من أنه بالفعل جاءت من المكان
the seller said they did.
الذي يقول بائعها أنه جاءت منها
And murder suspects have been tracked
ويتم ملاحقة القتلى
using their clothing,
عبر ملابسهم
certainly in the U.K., to within an area
وتحديدا في بريطانيا حيث يتم تحديد منطقة
that's small enough that you can send in tracker dogs
صغيرة بما يكفي لإرسال كلب تعقب
to find the murder victim.
لكي يجدوا ضحية جريمة القتل
So, you can tell from a piece of clothing
أي أنه يمكنك بواسطة قطعة قماش
to within about a kilometer or so,
تحديد منطقة بعدة كيلومترات أو حتى
where that piece of clothing has been recently
معرفة الأماكن التي كانت موجودة بها - تلك القطعة - مؤخراً
and then send in dogs.
ومن ثم إرسال الكلاب
And finally, in a rather grizzly way,
وأخيراً .. وبدلا من الطرق الصعبة
the Bosnia war crimes;
في جرائم حرب البوسنة
some of the people brought to trial were brought to trial
تم جلب بعض المتهمين لمحاكمتهم
because of the evidence from pollen,
بسبب أدلة تعتمد على حبوب اللقاح
which showed that bodies had been buried,
والتي بينت أنهم كانوا موجودون في المكان الذي دفنت فيه جثث الضحايا
exhumed and then reburied somewhere else.
أو نبشت منه ومن ثم تم إعادة دفنها
I hope I've opened your eyes,
أأمل بأن أكون قد نبهتكم إلى شيء ما
if you'll excuse the visual pun, (Laughter)
وعليكم أن تعذروا التخفي البصري
to some of pollen's secrets.
لبعض حبات اللقاح
This is a horse chestnut.
هذه تعود للكستناء
There is an invisible beauty all around us,
هناك الكثير من الجمال الغير مرئي حولنا
each grain with a story to tell ...
وكل حبة لقاح لديها قصة ترويها
each of us, in fact, with a story to tell
وكل واحد منا في الحقيقة لديه قصة يرويها
from the pollen fingerprint that's upon us.
من خلال حبات اللقاح المتعلقة بنا
Thank you to the colleagues at Kew,
أشكر الزملاء في مخابر " كيو "
and thank you to palynologists everywhere.
وشكراً لكل خبراء حبات اللقاح في كل مكان
(Applause)
(تصفيق)